this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software developers take your marks it's
time to upgrade your data platform to
enter systems iris it's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible it's time to
use any data from any source it's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces so what are
you waiting for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborates
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done tomorrow's next
breakthroughs are waiting for you today
inner system's iris Data Platform the
fastest way to build applications ready
set code start coding for free visit
inner systems comm slash tried to try
iris rich Harris is the creator of the
open source projects felt for work rich
is a graphics editor at The New York
Times investigation team prior to the
New York Times rich worked at the
Guardian for several years working as an
interactive developer and editor in
addition to spelt rich has also authored
the open source project roll up a
JavaScript bundler similar to web pack
and parcel rich thanks for coming onto
software engineering radio good to be
here thanks I haven't me absolutely so
let's kick things off at a very high
level what is felt and what sparked its
creation so I'm sure that some listeners
of this podcast will be familiar with
projects like react and view and angular
and things like that which are
essentially ways of building user
interfaces in a more declarative way
than we used to in the in the old days
of things like jQuery and these are very
popular they're kind of the standard way
that people build applications nowadays
a few years ago I was using a similar
framework predecessor to spelt called
reactive to build interactive web
applications that in my paper with the
Guardian and was coming increasingly
concerned about the amount of JavaScript
that we were sending down to the
particularly because a lot of our
readership was shifting at that time
from desktop to mobile and frankly a lot
of these front-end frameworks they they
are too big they involve too much
JavaScript and so started thinking about
what a potential solution to that could
look like and after some conversations
that I'd had that year I've been
thinking about whether or not it would
be possible to take the same declarative
code that we used to build applications
using component frameworks and kind of
compile that down to this optimized Ben
in a JavaScript form so in essence while
you're writing the high-level code that
is very easy to read and write and
understand the compiler is turning it
into the kind of direct Dom manipulation
that browsers are very efficient at and
it turned out to be a pretty successful
experiment we managed to get our
JavaScript payload sizes down quite
substantially by using this technique
and it kind of went on from there until
last year and I think about April of
last year we decided to overhaul the
developer experience as well so now we
have this very small very fast form of
JavaScript application people seem to
agree is a really quite nice development
experience so that's what it is it's a
way of building interactive web
applications without penalizing the user
with big JavaScript payloads or slow Dom
updates and any of the other problems
that have historically affected some
applications built with these frameworks
so compiler as a framework is a pretty
unusual way of doing things on the
front-end so why they need to go
compiled well the way that these things
traditionally work is you will write
your application declaratively and then
you will take that declarative form and
it will pass over to some library which
then has to kind of interpret it and
figure out what to do with it and so
classic example would be the virtual Dom
technique that's found in libraries like
react the way that react application
typically works is conceptually at least
your re-rendering the entire UI on every
state change and I should stress that
that's not actually what's happening
because there are all kinds of
optimizations so that you're only ever
dating a subtree of your application in
most cases but essentially you're you're
kind of rear end during the world from
scratch
and then you're handing it off to this
engine which then has to figure out what
changed from the last time that happened
and so it goes through this different
process figures out what on the page is
now out of date and then it makes that
change on the page and that that works
for the vast majority of applications
that is fast enough but there are costs
to that number one you have the
different process itself which is not
free and you know we've seen all kinds
of interesting strategies to mitigate
the cost of that defense number two in
order to get that virtual Dom structure
you need to rerun a lot of user code and
that's actually where a lot of the
performance crotches tend to be because
it's really easy to write code that
isn't all that well optimized if you
have something that is this kind of
statically analyzable form then you
actually don't need to run user code
nearly as often and then thirdly in
order to actually do that reconciliation
you need to have something that is
capable of doing that different process
which means that you're shipping that
javascript with every single application
that uses those frameworks and so by
taking the compiled approach you can
kind of chip away at each of those
problems individually and so what's step
in the build process does this all
happen
so you've got your code you're ready to
start compiling it down walk me through
the process from saving the code to
getting it to the browser so you'll
write your application into a series of
components we use a dot svelte extension
typically and this felt file is it's
kind of a superset of HTML so you have
your markup and you have some script
that defines components behavior you
have some Styles which define the
component styles and their scope to the
component but that's something that we
can probably come back to and you just
import that file like you would import
any other JavaScript module so in the
same way that you might do import foo
from dot slash food is you can do import
app from dot slash app dot spelled and
then what your JavaScript bundler does
at that point is because you've used the
salt plug-in with your web pack config
or your roller config or your parcel
config it knows that when it encounters
a file with the dots felt extension it
needs to hand the code off to the spell
compiler which will turn it into a
JavaScript module and so as far as your
bundler is concerned it's just like any
other JavaScript class
Babel is a source of source compiler
also known as a transpiler for
JavaScript latest features so is it
similar to Babel in terms of how it
compiles down the code I think there
probably are a lot of similarities in
the techniques that are being used there
are definitely some differences as well
spell is not using Babel under the hood
it's using its own compiler it has its
own HTML parser and it uses a JavaScript
parser called acorn and a CSS parser
called CSS tree and it takes your input
code and it hands it off to those three
separate parses and then from that we've
got this abstract syntax tree and then
there's a process of walking that
abstract syntax tree and understanding
all of the different parts of your
application understanding how the Styles
relate to the mark-up understanding what
kind of variables that are in a
component which things could change you
know which bits of of state we have that
could possibly affect what needs to get
rendered but the others at the other end
of that we have the JavaScript that gets
generated and it's as I say it's not
exactly the same process that Babel uses
but I imagine that it's pretty similar
not that I'm intimately familiar with
Babel source code because that's a quite
a chunky project that I haven't spent a
lot of time getting my hands dirty with
so would they actually be considered
alternatives to each other not really no
I'm babel is a very extensible system
and i think you probably could write
something akin to spelt
within the babel ecosystem but Babel is
really more focused on fairly small
syntax transformations to take code that
targets the newest versions of the
JavaScript spec or the tank scripts back
and compiles it down to something that
can run in basically every brow every
browser that people are using
whereas felt is doing something
different it's taking your your
declarative code and it's turning it
into something that is a completely
different type of program it's turning
it into imperative JavaScript so even
though you can kind of look at a piece
of markup in a svelte component and you
can trace it to the JavaScript that ends
up getting generated by the spell
compiler it's not like we're just doing
a little bit of syntax transformation
here
a little bit of sense a transformation
there we're actually completely
rewriting the code or not even rewriting
we're generating a program from scratch
based on the blueprints that you the
architect of the program have provided
so this means that you're actually
transforming the code into imperative
JavaScript completely rewriting it Moret
how do you make the code imperative
that's a good question so it probably
helps to think about how you would write
an application 10 years ago if you're
approaching the same problem but in the
the pre framework era and you're using
the newer JavaScript so let's say we
want to build a button that increments a
counter every time you click on it you
might do something like var button
equals document create element and then
pass it the string button and that gives
you your baton element and then you
might have a variable representing the
count of our count equals 0 and then you
might have an update function and just
call it function update inside that you
might say count plus equals 1 and then
button dot text content equals and then
the count variable and then finally you
just need to do button dot add event
listener and then pass it the update
function and then all you need to do is
is mount that but an element to the body
of your application and you have an
interactive clicky button thing and it
works that is that is the process by
which you update something on the screen
what's felt is doing is essentially
trying to recreate the code that you
would write by hand in that situation
except that rather than writing all of
that stuff out by hand you're literally
just right in the market for a button
and then you're putting inside the
button the an expression that represents
the current count and then add an event
listener declaratively and svelte will
turn that into button dot add event
listener and so on in that way it's able
to basically get the same performance
characteristics that you would generally
get if you're writing these things by
hand alright so you're basically be
making in the manual process of event
listening and event delegation that
would normally be done in vanilla
JavaScript and you're doing that through
the compiler because that's the area
where people are they messing it up the
most or is it just the
wrote pieces that are sub optimized it
seems like for you know if you have HTML
CSS and JavaScript
the main actual interactive JavaScript
you're writing in spelt probably isn't
being optimized that much it's more the
stuff that's on the HTML layer that
you're trying to optimize is that is
that a fair assumption it is yeah so
when the thing that people found in that
era when we were building stuff with
jQuery it was that it's really easy to
write buggy code that way and we even
have a phrase for it spaghetti code
because you can't think of your
application in a very holistic way you
have to sort of trace the possible code
paths and think about how the user
interacting with the application can
result in a particular code path being
taken and so you're thinking not just in
like the two-dimensional terms of what
the code looks like on screen and what
the output is going to get it is going
to appear as but you're sort of thinking
in this third by mention which is time
as the user interacts with the
application and it's incredibly
difficult and and even experienced
programmers get this stuff wrong all the
time a compiler doesn't have that
problem it allows you to think in that
sort of two-dimensional way of just you
know this is what the application looks
like for a given state and then it does
the hard work of making that a bug-free
experience the other thing that people
found was that it can be quite difficult
to write vanilla JavaScript applications
in a way that is performant because it's
easy to get into a situation where
you're over querying the Dom or over
updating the Dom because you don't want
to keep track of the very small state
change deltas each time so you tend to
sort of just throw a whole bunch in each
state in your application and kind of
let it figure itself out and again a
compiler can be a little bit more
conservative than you would typically be
if you're writing the code yourself so I
think it helps to think of spelt as kind
of an assistant in a way like your
instead of you know you're no longer the
plumber and the electrician you're the
architect so you can think about what
the house should look like without
having to worry about where all the
cabling is is having to go
and because of that you're you know
you're spending your your cognitive time
at a place where it's better suited
right so when you think about creating a
click function all you have to think
about is I'm adding this click property
onto this tag and spelt belt is smart
enough to go okay I see a click property
I'm going to handle the event delegation
piping everything up together so you no
longer have to worry about that that's
exactly it yeah you just need to focus
on what the application looks like for a
given piece of state and how that state
changes and everything else flows from
that and most frameworks rely on babel
to handle language upgrades how does
felt handle this so we we don't really
get involved in in that stuff spelt
generates modern JavaScript if you want
to use something that is beyond modern
JavaScript then you might need to
pre-process your component code if you
want to target older browsers then you
might need to post process the output at
the spell compiler but spell is
basically targeting modern browsers with
the option to transpile for older
browsers if you need it and so we we
don't actually have babel as part of our
default project templates that's
something that people can bring if it's
something that they need for for their
user base okay so you can actually stack
the two on top of each other and you'll
still get ya the optimized output okay
changing directions of it I want to
compare spelt to the other sort of big
frameworks in the front-end world
angular view and react starting with
angular you know with angular it's
backed by Google it's huge it's bloated
the upside is that you've got everything
but the kitchen sink the downside is
that because you have everything but the
kitchen sink you might get more than you
need and it can be very large and slow
so are you competing in the same space
given that you are a full stack you
support HTML CSS JavaScript and all the
interactivity that comes with it we're
definitely competing in overlapping
spaces I think and actually you know I
don't like the word competing because
there's room for all of these different
projects and angular is it certainly has
a reputation that you describe of being
a little bit let's say soft around the
edges but the more recent versions and
particularly the next version which I
think is going to be I think it's
angular 9 maybe
totally kept track is taking a pretty
similar route to spelt of taking your
templates and compiling them into a more
optimal form so because of that angular
apps are gonna get smaller they're gonna
get faster and they're already I think
that they're pretty performing in that
current state but yes you're right
angular has a whole bunch of extra stuff
with it like you get
internationalization out of the box and
you get like a very opinionated testing
story and you get HTTP helpers and all
sorts of things that spell is not
concerned with spell is designed to be
just the UI and just the the state
management that you need to build a UI
and everything else is kind of left to
you as the app developer to figure out
if it's something that you need and if
so to get the version of that thing that
best suits your your app because I don't
think that a team is as small as felts
could possibly have the best possible
answer to all of the questions that a
framework like angular attempts to
answer does spelt have a modular plug-in
system so that if you are missing
something that smoke can't provide that
you can find it somewhere else
yeah I mean inside and inside the script
tag of a spelt component it's just a
regular JavaScript module so you can
import absolutely anything from the NPM
ecosystem just as though you're writing
anything else it does have quite a lot
of stuff built in that is UI focused
that a lot of frameworks don't tend to
include so it has a pretty decent state
management system built-in it has
helpers for doing animations and
transitions has easing functions and
things like that because a lot of people
using spell are using it to build user
interfaces that are fluid and have lots
of motion and you know I personally
think that's an incredibly important and
somewhat overlooked part of UI
development on the web and so it does
include all of that stuff but you don't
pay for it unless you're using it the
way that the framework is designed is
you only import the things that you need
and the rest of it will just kind of get
discarded when you're not using it and
the compiler too will only compile in
the bits of the framework that are
actually relevant to your
application and so that's one of the
ways that cell taps don't end up
becoming huge is because everything is
kind of optimized for the specific use
case to which you're putting it so it's
working similar to web hack then it's
able to figure out what pieces are not
needed and then just wipe them away yeah
yeah I mean to put it more more
accurately it's generating JavaScript
that that a JavaScript bundle and knows
how to treat it
okay so it's acting as both a compiler
and a bundler in a sense it's not acting
as a bundler no there is a one-to-one
correspondence between your components
and the JavaScript module that svelt
generates as far as the bundler is
concerned it's it gets handed a bunch of
JavaScript because that's happened as
well you know they have a series of
transformations which take some input
and it's a JavaScript and then the
bundler job is to figure out how those
pieces of JavaScript interrelate spelt
does not get involved in having said
that one thing that we occasionally talk
about is whether it would be possible to
generate even smaller faster code if
spell the compiler had a kind of a
bird's-eye view of your entire
application rather than focusing on each
component in isolation because there are
certainly times when you know you might
be setting a property on a component
that never changes and because spell is
only looking at one component at a time
the child component will have to
generate code to anticipate that
property changing even though it doesn't
actually change and so you know having
said that there's this one-to-one
correspondence and spell is not a
bundler and it does not take on the
responsibilities of a bundler the make
of a time in future when compiler
frameworks do start to drift in the
direction of having a kind of a more
opinionated and holistic view about
about how your input code should should
turn into the JavaScript that runs in in
the users browser right it sounds like
you could even start to get into the
space of something like node where you
have a package.json file and you're
actually specifying what are the source
route files for all of your whole
project so then you could start to build
this sort of source tree that you're
talking about so to be truly truly
optimized in the output yeah and
actually when you say that it starts to
sound a little bit like spell scan
project sapper which is so tell is a
complaint of frameworks tapper is an
application framework that is designed
to make it easy to build fairly
ambitious applications fairly quickly
including subtype rendering and code
splitting and all of these are the
modern conveniences that people expect
when they're building an app and it it
kind of does that it takes the same
mindset of trying to generate code that
is optimal for your component and
generating code that is lots more for
your application it will look at your
folder structure which it interprets as
a routing structure or routing structure
for the Americans and it will actually
generate a router on demand based on the
routes that you have in your application
which is a little bit different to how
these things work elsewhere so yeah it's
a it's a mindset that I think has a lot
of different avenues to explore and
we're just kind of beginning to
understand what some of those Havanese
are so getting back to the other
framework comparisons just a sort of
transition out of angular one of the
frameworks that seems most comparable to
spelt is view because they're both
lightweight fast and independent so why
would someone choose felt overview given
the similarities it's a pretty good
question so spelt has some fairly clear
advantages over view two in terms of
performance and particularly for smaller
apps in terms of bundle size some of
those advantages are going to be less
pronounced with when view 3 comes out
because V 3 is is actually starting to
do some fairly similar things to view in
terms of compiling view components into
optimized JavaScript so it's really I
think gonna come down to a matter of
personal preference in a lot of cases
when I look at view components and Spell
components side-by-side you tend to
notice that the spelt component is quite
a bit smaller because we've developed
this I mean it's basically a language
that allows you to express a user
interface in the most concise way
possible view because of its of its
history it doesn't allow you to be quite
as concise
so you have to write a little bit more
code when you're writing in you app but
on the flip side if you're using view
then number one there are a lot more
view jobs than there asphalt jobs number
two the ecosystem is much bigger number
three it's arguably better supported it
has a larger core team and you know if
you're stuck with a problem in your view
app then it's more likely that you'll be
able to find a relevant Stack Overflow
answer etc so you know I preferred to
write fault code I'm not going to be
switch interview three because I prefer
the development experience of using
spelt and I prefer the the priorities
that the spelt project has but v3 is
going to be a really compelling choice
and I think that we're probably going to
see definitely at least some movement
from the react community over to the
view 3 community because I think it
starts to address some of the concerns
that the react folks have had and people
should be pretty excited about the
prospect of having all of these things
to choose from
speaking of react react is arguably the
largest free merky in the front-end
space so while with angular and arguably
incontestably with with angular and view
they're really sought as the
alternatives if you're green fielding a
project whereas react is the de facto
standard so for someone who's using
react it's more likely the case that
they're being convinced to move to spelt
rather than being on sort of the same
plane with angular view yeah if you are
react developer what are you doing to
convince your manager your team lead to
start using spelt as an alternative I
know I don't know I'd be interested to
hear what people are saying in that
situation I would again point to the
source code comparisons I find that on
average when I rewrite a react component
as a small component tends to be about
40% smaller so you're you're writing
code in what seems to me to be a much
more efficient way and when you're
writing less code you're not just saving
yourself time you're not just giving the
next person who reads the code less to
do but you're writing a more stable
application because there's a pretty
direct correspondence between the lines
of code that you're in in your app and
the number of bugs are and this is a
thing that applies across languages you
know there isn't a whole lot of science
on it but that the literature that I
have looked at suggests that any code
base is gonna have a certain number of
bugs and that grows that number grows
super linearly as code size grows so if
you're using spelt instead of react you
will be writing this code your
application will probably be smaller
especially if you use in code splitting
it will almost certainly be faster and
you don't have to worry about CSS in j/s
or anything like that because it's all
kind of built into the framework same
with state management you don't need to
figure out how to use a particular state
management system inside your react app
because it's already kind of built in so
I think there are some pretty concrete
advantages that svelt has overreact on
the flip side again you know there's a
ton of stuff that is really really great
about react the ecosystem is huge
there's so many exciting projects that
people are building around react there's
a project called react 3 fiber for
example by the author of react spring
you put those two things together and
you can build these incredibly rich 3d
WebGL apps using your react skills we're
trying to do the same thing in this Val
ecosystem but it's nowhere near as
developed because you know we don't have
the benefit of a huge community of react
developers all trying to like build on
top of all of the territory that
reactors made available so you know if
people are building react apps then they
shouldn't feel under any pressure to
switch away from them because it's a
pretty great framework and it's not
going anywhere but you know if you're
starting a new project then I would
definitely say take a look at the
alternatives because there are some I
think pretty stands pretty substantial
advantages developers take your marks
it's time to upgrade your data platform
to inner systems iris it's time to
deliver complex mission-critical
applications in the fastest route
possible it's time to use any data from
any source it's time to embed analytics
and create in
active user interfaces so what are you
waiting for choose your language choose
your tools choose your environment
collaborates build faster and deploy
more efficiently done and done
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today inner systems iris
Data Platform the fastest way to build
applications ready set code start coding
for free visit inner systems comm slash
tried to try iris other any particular
use cases where perhaps your react
developer you want to try something new
and there are particular performance
conscious cases where you need to really
focus on a smaller bundle size or you
know render performance can you think of
some just smaller tasks that one might
be able to sprinkle into an existing
code base certainly anything involving
animation react does not do well an
animation that's just kind of a known
limitation of the way that that the
framework operates on a fundamental
level because it has to do quite a lot
of work for each state change you know
you're not always going to be able to
get everything done inside your frame
budget which is typically you know
you've got around 8 milliseconds in
which to do everything the react team
have kind of said that's not enough time
so instead of trying to get everything
done inside a frame budget we're gonna
build a system called concurrent mode
which allows you to kind of spread that
work over multiple frames which is
incredibly smart and ingenious and it
opens up some pretty interesting
possibilities but it kind of shows that
animation is maybe not a big priority
anything that is for lower powered
devices I would say take a look at
svelte and when I talk about lower
powered devices I don't just mean cheap
phones that are used in the developing
world I'm also talking about things like
Smart TVs and embedded systems in point
of sale devices and stuff like that
people have found that it's just not
possible to get the right amount of
performance using react in those
contexts whereas they've built the same
applications in spelt and it's been a
far more pleasant experience so that's a
niche that we're doing pretty well in is
Smart TVs and stuff I
and even though most about developers
these days aren't building those kinds
of apps I think it's probably going to
be more and more of the industry over
the next few years I think we're going
to see this transition in focus towards
the I like to call it the embedded web
and that's a place where a framework
like svelt can really help you on the
other end of the spectrum so we got
react as the most dominant player but on
the other end we have these much smaller
ones which are very similar to your
space something like Phoenix live view
closure script Elm sort of compiled down
languages that are inspired by other
languages like Haskell or closure how do
you see yourself fitting in that space I
think there's a there's a lot of
conceptual overlap between what spelt is
doing on what they're doing I'm ashamed
to admit I haven't really spent any time
with any of those things even though
they I'm deeply curious about all of
them I would say that it's felt is
probably targeting a slightly different
audience like the people who are they're
already sold on functional programming
and they you know they really want a
system that guarantees that they're not
going to have any runtime bugs and stuff
like that those frameworks are
incredibly appealing from that point of
view something like Phoenix live view
which basically does all of the work on
the server and like ships Delta's to the
client and the client has to apply them
that is a truly fascinating concept but
you know there's a whole class of
applications for which that's just
completely impractical so you know I'm
I'm glad that all of this
experimentation is happening but for me
spell is the sweet spot between the
benefits of the compiled approach that
these frameworks are taking and the
approach ability of something that is
based around HTML CSS and JavaScript it
doesn't really have much of a learning
curve whereas those other things you
basically got to be invested enough to
learn an entirely new language from
scratch so we've looked all the other
frameworks we know we want to start
sprinkling in some spelt and you know
for these bigger development teams some
people actually know react before they
know JavaScript do you think that spelt
has that same level of or approach
ability where people can just dive right
into spelt without having necessarily to
have a background in JavaScript so I
actually got a really touching email the
other day from
from a chap who runs a coding bootcamp
in Egypt where the it's a nonprofit that
is it's providing tuition for refugees
from surrounding countries and he said
the kindest thing he basically said that
these people came in with no computer
science background and no real
experience of web development or
anything like that and they started
writing spelt and it empowered them to
start building things without having to
know all of the fundamentals and without
having to spend like the first ten weeks
learning all of these idiosyncratic dumb
api's and the ways that they behave
differently between browsers and all of
that nonsense they could just start
building stuff so empirically yes people
are using spell in that manner they are
able to build things much quicker than
they would otherwise have been and it's
not I don't think preventing them from
learning the fundamentals of JavaScript
it's just allowing them to get to a
point where that is an appealing thing
to do as opposed to that incredibly
demoralizing beginner process that so
many of us have kind of had to trudge
through that's incredible
Wow so if you're not new to programming
are there any tips or gotchas you have
for those that are new to spelt it
really has but I'm also trying to figure
out if there really are any gotchas
we've tried to make the whole thing is
kind of idiomatic is as possible so that
things are more or less self-explanatory
definitely some people when they first
encounter spelt code or a little bit
though what is this because it doesn't
behave exactly how they're used to when
you assign to a value inside a spelt
component you're actually causing that
component to update and that's not
something that happens in JavaScript
JavaScript is not a reactive language
normally if you change something you
then have to you know call a function or
otherwise do something that causes the
page to update in response to your state
changes but it's felt kind of takes care
of that magically and definitely when
people first see that a little bit
that's not sure how I feel about that
similarly there are a couple of places
where in order to get the programming
experience
that we want within the constraints that
we're working in we've had to kind of
calm endure a little bits of the
language so the export keyword for
example we use the Xbox keyword to
define the components interface to the
outside world and it's a little bit
backwards from how people normally use
the export keyword because we're saying
these are the the bits of data that you
can pass into this component as opposed
to saying this is the stuff that that
gets pushed out at the component if that
makes any sense at all we're also using
the JavaScript labelled statement which
is a fairly esoteric piece of syntax
that most people haven't encountered
we're using that to define what we call
reactive statements this is code that
reruns whenever any of the dependencies
of that statement change so for example
we use the dollar label for this if you
have a piece of code that is dollar a
equals B plus C then whenever the values
of B and C change the value of a will
also change where is normally in
JavaScript if you have a line that says
a equals B plus C that just happens once
and then after that you need to manually
re-invite that code each time so those
all of this magic to make the process of
building an application a little bit
smoother and a little bit faster but it
definitely takes a little bit of getting
used to if particularly if you haven't
used a reactive framework before but but
even even in general like a lot of
people come to it and it takes them a
minute to get used to it I'd actually
love to dive into some of this magic now
that you're starting to talk about the
nuts and bolts of the of the language I
loved it and just talk more about it
under the hood we're starting with a
very simple question is it all written
in JavaScript no actually the compiler
is written in typescript I'm a big
typescript fan myself I try and write
typescript almost exclusively over
JavaScript these days which is ironic
because spell that present doesn't have
good typescript integration if you're
writing a svelte component then you're
writing JavaScript you're not writing
tight scripts and that's one of the
things that we really need to get around
to pretty soon because it's one of the
most requested features is better times
integration okay and it is the core code
of
a compiler in the traditional sense so
it has a parser a lexer an AST all those
kinds of things how is it laid out
architectural e we do have our own HTML
parser I'm not sure if there's like a
technical family of compilers that this
belongs to and I already have the
education to know if if we're even doing
everything completely wrong but it
basically reason your your markup and
turns it into a tree structure and then
at a later phase that tree structure
gets walked over and understood and
manipulated the other parts the ast the
the style tree and the JavaScript tree
they're taken care of by external NPM
packages CSS tree for the styles and a
con for the JavaScript I would never
want to have to write a JavaScript
parser because it's a huge complex
language and luckily we don't have to
because brilliant people have already
made some packages that make that
possible
but yeah beyond that I think it probably
resembles a conventional compiler fairly
closely but again I don't really have
the the background to know the ways in
which were the same or different yeah
and honestly you had touched on this
earlier building out the abstract syntax
tree and comparing the tree of objects
within HTML that it very much is exactly
what a traditional compiler is doing and
it sounds like that that that you are
doing this yourself is the big
performance draw compared to something
like virtual Dom because it I know in
most frameworks they're building this
tree in this virtual Dom to do
comparisons that obviously has a lot of
overhead because it's you're essentially
building a duplicate of that tree and
doing a comparison yeah so how are you
achieving those performance gains with
your own tree against you know not
having to use virtual Dom essentially
we're shifting the work out of the
browser and into the build step it's not
exactly this the same work that's
happening but you can think of it that
way you're taking that different process
and you're doing it at compile time
essentially and so the code that gets
generated is just a bunch of if
statements if this value has changed
then update this text mode if that value
has changed I think that text mode and
because of that the state change is
essentially a linear sequence of
operations which is pretty
to run through its the code that gets
generated is the kind of code that
browsers are good at running with all
these performance gains are there any
drawbacks so because now it's a compiled
framework are there things that svelt
cannot do the raw in the sense that
because components have to be statically
analyzable you can't just put anything
inside an expression inside your markup
it has to be something that is going to
get turned into text whereas with a
virtual Dom there's this really
interesting property which is that your
UI is just data and your data is just UI
these these things are kind of one in
the same substance and so you can inside
an expression inside JSX in a react
component for example your expression
can evaluate to a piece of text it can
evaluate to a component it can evaluate
to an element or an array of all of
those things or a fragment or you know
this that and the other and so you have
this infinite complexity in the things
that you can build whereas we've felt
you don't have quite the same amount of
flexibility on paper now for me the
interesting question is not whether or
not you have that flexibility it's
whether or not you have the flexibility
that you need to build your application
and so far we haven't encountered a
situation where there's something that
you can do in react that there isn't
also a very easy and idiomatic way to do
in svelte so technically yes there are
limitations because of the language that
we've chosen
but in practice not so much it's more of
an academic question okay and then are
there other pieces other aspects of
front-end development that can be
limiting with spelt so for example the
common ones that come up for react or
angular are SEO and accessibility mainly
because with JSX you have to make sure
that every single property can be
covered within that within that
framework and then with SEO that's a
really big one because of the fact that
everything is getting dirty checked and
so it's you don't necessarily have all
of that content available and you're
looking at a page and so are you also
running into these same sort of concerns
from people who are using spelt not so
much so I think these these issues are
slightly separate too
from from framework choice because I
think all frameworks nowadays support so
when we talk about SEO I think what
we're really talking about is whether or
not applications can be server rendered
because in the model that the web
development community there's been
flirting with for a bit the single page
app model where you essentially have a
blank page and then Java scripts kind of
squirts everything inside that blank
page that historically has not been
great for SEO because historically
search engines didn't really know what
to do that and that's changing a bit
Google is much better at understanding
the content of a page after JavaScript
has been executed on it these days but
there is still very much a benefit to
doing server-side rendering of your
application which is to say sending some
HTML to the browser and then augmenting
it once the JavaScript executes to send
it into an interactive application and
svelte is really really good a
server-side rendering because it's a
compiler and it's targeting a different
environment it can just turn your
components into basically a set of
string concatenation functions so it's
incredibly fast rather than having to
construct the component tree and then
serialize it in the way that other
frameworks do so I I guess what I'm
saying is that all frameworks can in
theory get SEO done right but spelt is
particularly well positioned to do so
because server-side rendering is so good
in spelt and sapper the application
framework that I mentioned has
server-side rendering out-of-the-box on
the accessibility friend I think again
this is not necessarily so much to do
with the frameworks that we use I think
it's more about the quality of the
marker that we as application developers
are writing but also the quality of the
component ecosystem that you're using
and so the react ecosystem for example
has some really brilliant component
libraries some of which take
accessibility very seriously and if
you're using those component libraries
or if using one of the big design
systems that are out there then you're
not going to have too many problems I
would hope with that accessibility as
long as you the application developer
have at least some understanding of what
the
the challenges are on this felt side we
take accessibility pretty seriously if
you write markup that fail some
accessibility test then the compiler
will warn you about it so for example if
you have an image tag then you forget to
add the alt attribute it will yell at
you and so I think between all of the
different frameworks and all of the
different techniques that with kind of
converging on I think as a community
we're getting pretty good at solving
these SEO problems in these accesses
accessibility problems and I think the
the common trope of you know the hitch
the JavaScript framework developer
ending up writing a web app that is all
but useless for people except the ones
on expensive IMAX you have you know no
accessibility hurdles or anything like
that it is really unfair actually
nowadays pretty much whatever framework
you choose you know you have a like a
good SEO and accessibility story waiting
for you
that's actually pretty surprising to
hear that spelt is that robust in its
compiler and giving its compiler or
warnings it so almost sounds very
similar to the way that you can provide
all those configurations with typescript
are you planning on creating a very
robust sort of compiler warning system
that spans across things simply beyond
the framework not beyond the framework I
mean it we're really focused on making
sure that your components written as
well as they can be but this is one of
the great things about being a compiler
because we're not shipping this code to
the browser because it all just lives
inside your node modules folder we can
include features that other frameworks
with ballcap and accessibility warnings
is one of those things like it it just
wouldn't occur to you to include
accessibility accessibility warnings in
the core of a framework right and that's
exactly what surprised me right yeah and
that's a good thing though I think I
think we need to have more of that
available to developers so they can be
aware of these things so are there other
aspects of the framework for your
compiler warnings that you're also
including if you could just run through
some of those be cool because I I didn't
realize that accessibility was one or
they're others similar to that like in
performance
I think that's the big one certainly we
you know we have things like unused
property warnings and unused CSS
selectors is another big one because the
styles in your component being looked at
in the context of the markup for that
component we're able to say that oh you
know this selector over here you've got
some Styles for for the selectable
you're not actually using that selector
anywhere in your markup so you should
get rid of it and at the same time the
compiler will itself get rid of it so
that you're never actually shipping any
unused CSS to your users that is another
pretty neat feature that you can't
really get without our compiler and and
I guess there are probably some ways
that we could maybe you know figure out
ways to have footman's fine-tuning tips
emitted by the compiler but that's it's
not something that we have currently are
you getting a lot of performance gains
from that unused CSS I feel like in this
fronting community that's the biggest
one everybody feels like that's a super
hard problem to tackle but if you can
get that right you can save so much I
mean so many pages if you look at them
through like Google lighthouse they'll
say that you're not using 99% of the CSS
that you have bundled up so are you is
actually helping application developers
with that feature I mean I think it must
be but I've had this experience so many
times where you know before spell I had
this experience so many times where I
would write some code and my colleagues
write some code and we weren't sure what
the CSS that that the other person had
written was doing and you don't want to
delete it because it's so hard to tell
what effects a piece of CSS has because
it's all inherently global and so you
have this a phenomenon of the
append-only stylesheet right you never
delete CSS you only ever add to it
unless it you get to the point where
you've realized it you've got 200
kilobytes of the bloody stuff and you
need to start over because styles in
spell are component scopes you just
never reach that problem and so I think
it's probably fair to say that a spell
tap will typically have less CSS than
most apps purely by virtue of the fact
that you're not writing anything that
that need and then I also want to just
touch on this lightly before we move off
the framework internals so you had
mentioned this earlier testing is
another big one yeah how is it tested
and our bugs introduced by the compiler
haha bugs introduced by the compiler
yeah I wish I could say that they never
were but all software has bugs and there
are definitely been times when we've
released a new version of the compiler
and it has introduced bugs into people's
code we're usually pretty good about
fixing those quite probably but yeah I
can't I can't claim that we're perfect
in that regard testing it's it's kind of
like testing anything else really
because the compiler is just turning
your component into a JavaScript class
you can test it in the way that you
would test any other JavaScript class I
think this is something that we've been
criticized for as a community we don't
have a really opinionated solution
around testing like we don't have inside
our default project template like a
boilerplate that you can just kind of
start filling out with your own tests
and the reason for that is that we
haven't really figured out what is worth
testing in this context because so many
people when they start writing tests for
their user interface are essentially
just recreating the tests that already
exists inside the framework the
framework scientists we've felt has
thousands of tests and like the idea
that you need to check that if you know
you pass in the number 42 as one of the
props to your component then the number
42 is the thing that gets rendered
inside the dom is like what value does
that ring so you know I I guess we'll
figure that out as more and more people
start yelling at us about the lack of an
opinionated testing story but in the
meantime it's just JavaScript you can
test it however you like it works with
any testing framework people use ever
chests people use with Amaka people use
it with you know spell testing library
from the from Kent Dodds is suite of
testing libraries there's they're always
there's plenty of ways so switching
gears
I noticed that back in April he released
version 3 of spelt yeah how has it
received what are the big changes that
were part of version 3 it was received
in
well we we really stuck the landing that
time around we've been working on it for
a very long time and we've been kind of
talking about it in our own community
and hyping it up and people were
starting to get excited but it was that
at that stage the svelt community was it
was very small but then in April there
was sort of a compliments of things we
launched version 3 there was a video
from a conference that I had attended
where I've spoken about spelled in
Israel you've got a low front end which
is a really wonderful conference there
was a podcast episode and there was a
blog post all of those things kind of
came together in the the perfect hacker
news launch post and so for the people
who like to read about stuff they could
read the blog post people who prefer to
listen they had the podcast people who
prefer to watch videos about this stuff
they had me standing on stage in Israel
waffling for half an hour and so because
of that I think we kind of hit all the
different targets simultaneously and we
kind of generated this this this wave of
hype and we've been riding it ever since
it was really good
not really through any kind of planning
it was all just very fortuitous and I
don't know if it's something that would
ever be able to repeat but it really
worked well for us the big change was
really around the developer experience
we essentially redesigned the component
or three authoring experience from the
ground up before that would been
constrained by some some bad API design
decisions that I had made in the very
first version of spelt and first felt
free we really kind of said what would
happen if you were to design the
component offering experience from
scratch what would it look like if you
just threw away all of the constraints
that you normally have to work with when
you're designing a component framework
and felt three was the result of that I
should say it was very largely inspired
by the release of react that included
react hooks because that kind of changed
people's perceptions of what authoring
could be like in a writing a component
with react hooks is much nicer than
writing component with react classes you
know spelt - we thought was nicer than
react with classes but react hooks kind
of
raise the bar and we wanted to try and
clear that bar and then it's a great
point that you touch on here which is
that and you also touched on this
earlier you don't need to necessarily
see these frameworks as adversarial or
in competition of each other definitely
no like you just said you were inspired
by it so what's helping every single
group is getting lifted up because of
the changes they're making so they're
all pushing each other to help the web
move forward in the right direction and
so that actually makes me think you
would set earlier that you three is
going to be a very big release and it's
gonna provide a lot of the features that
people are looking forward to sort of
smaller frameworks
is there anything from view three that
you're seeing that's now getting you
more amped up for the release of spelt
for like what are the things on the
horizon that you're seeing from these
other frameworks that are inspiring you
well view has always had really good
typescript integration or not maybe not
always but for a long time it's had
really good typescript integration and I
and I definitely want to steal that at
some point the other thing that I'm
looking at quite enviously is react
suspense which is not yet stable but you
know a lot of people are talking about
react suspense and the thing that that's
gonna enable which is to to make it much
easier to deal with a synchrony in
components at the moment it's quite easy
to build an application that has a bunch
of loading spinners for example or you
know flickering when you switch between
tabs if something needs to be fetched
over the network and and the react team
have really been focused on solving that
problem because it it affects the
product that they're using it for
Facebook and so that's something that I
would definitely like to look at
stealing but you're right you know do
all of these frameworks do learn from
each other a lot and I genuinely believe
that a rising tide lifts all boats and
it's kind of funny when we see people on
Twitter doing the whole framework war
thing and like people are fanboying over
their particular thing because you know
the reality is we're all kind of friends
to a large extent like I was in London a
couple of weeks back and I managed to
get a pint with Dominic Ganaway and
signal Pi on the react team and we're
all kind of just sharing ideas back and
forth and it's very collegial so yeah I
that's that's one of the nice things
about working on the web I think is that
people who are natural competitor
do feel like it's appropriate to share
ideas and share notes and you know
really try and solve these problems from
different angles but ultimately we're
all trying to say solve the same problem
to rule ultimately on the same team it's
nice with all that inspiration for the
next version of spelt do you need to
help with any of it
you know what's the best way for someone
to contribute to the project if they're
they're new to open source or if they're
a seasoned vet but they want to help
contribute to spelt oh wow
with our reishi list is is pretty
substantial at the moment to beat them
we definitely do need some help triaging
things but you know it is a it's a
little bit of a difficult code base for
someone to kind of dive into on a whim
but if people are motivated to get to
grips with the codebase and understand
how it works and start helping to merge
pull requests and close issues then they
should definitely come by our github
organization which is get home slash
felt yes they should come by our discord
chat room which is cell dev slash chat
redirects to a discord server and yes
start talking to us about what they
could bring to the project we everything
is volunteer based we don't have like a
formal team structure we don't have a
corporation behind us everything is kind
of done on a best effort basis which we
like you know we all have lives and
everyone is is by the same token welcome
to come and be part of the project and
we'll make sure to link to those URLs in
the in the show notes after the show
rich is there anything else you want to
touch on any other closing thoughts no
just that you know this this is a really
exciting time I think to be a web
developer where we're kind of in a place
now where we can start to think
seriously about what we want the ideal
experience is using the web to be like
and we can start building tools that
start to make those experiences possible
and you know and I'm glad to be a web
developer in 2020 even though the web is
sometimes a difficult platform to work
for I don't think there's anything quite
like it
rich it was a pleasure thank you very
much thank you developers take your
marks it's time to upgrade your data
platform to inner systems iris
it's time to deliver complex
mission-critical applications in the
fastest route possible it's time to use
any data from any source it's time to
embed analytics and create interactive
user interfaces so what are you waiting
for
choose your language choose your tools
choose your environment collaborate
build faster and deploy more efficiently
done and done
tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today inner system's
iris Data Platform the fastest way to
build applications
ready set code start coding for free
visit inner systems comm slash tried to
try iris thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SE -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening